<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Guillermo Esteves</title>
  <link href="http://blog.gesteves.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.gesteves.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-09-20T07:45:03-04:30</updated>
  <id>http://blog.gesteves.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Guillermo Esteves</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello, World</title>
    <link href="http://blog.gesteves.com/2011/09/19/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-19T17:14:00-04:30</updated>
    <id>http://blog.gesteves.com/2011/09/19/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After almost four years on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve decided it&amp;#8217;s time to switch blog platforms. My blog now runs on &lt;a href=&quot;http://octopress.org&quot;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heroku.com&quot;&gt;Heroku&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I&amp;#8217;m switching, and the reason I was using Tumblr in the first place, are a bit of a long story. I used to have a real blog, one I built myself in 2005 or so, when I was teaching myself Rails, and which I loved and updated frequently. However, a couple of years later, thanks to Venezuela&amp;#8217;s foreign currency restrictions which forbid us from spending more than US$400 a year in electronic payments, having a self-hosted blog running on paid hosting &amp;#8211; even cheap, shared hosting &amp;#8211; became untenable. Back then I was spending $9 a month at &lt;a href=&quot;http://railsplayground.com/&quot;&gt;Rails Playground&lt;/a&gt; to host my blog, which may not sound like a lot, but it added up to $108 a year &amp;#8211; over a quarter of what the venezuelan government allows me to spend on the Internet in a year. So, in 2008, when Tumblr began to take off in popularity, I decided to cancel my hosting plan, scrap my blog, write a small script to import all my content, and switch to Tumblr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had the advantage of not having to worry about servers or hosting costs while being flexible enough to allow me to tinker with the code and design to my heart&amp;#8217;s content, plus an amazing community that led me to meet some of the best friends I&amp;#8217;ve ever had. However, in the past few months I&amp;#8217;ve become quite dissatisfied with the service and the constant outages and downtime, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://staff.tumblr.com/post/10264121525/outage&quot;&gt;this recent&lt;/a&gt;, ongoing issue. I&amp;#8217;m also a bit uneasy with the content I post over there, because it&amp;#8217;s a strange mix of work/professional stuff and personal posts, reblogs, memes, and inside jokes that probably aren&amp;#8217;t interesting to anyone except my close circle of friends. So I thought it would be better to have a place that&amp;#8217;s just for &lt;a href=&quot;http://gestev.es/AGnN&quot;&gt;serious business&lt;/a&gt;, and leave Tumblr for personal posts, socializing with my friends, and sharing photos of cats. &lt;a href=&quot;http://tumblr.gesteves.com&quot;&gt;All-Encompassing Trip&lt;/a&gt; will keep going at its new address, but this will be my primary blog for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for my choice of platform, I chose &lt;a href=&quot;http://octopress.org&quot;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt; after reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgemmell.com&quot;&gt;Matt Gemmell&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgemmell.com/2011/09/12/blogging-with-octopress/&quot;&gt;rave about it&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#8217;ve always liked the idea of having a “&lt;a href=&quot;http://inessential.com/2011/03/16/a_plea_for_baked_weblogs&quot;&gt;baked&lt;/a&gt;” blog (i.e. one that&amp;#8217;s entirely static &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt;), and I&amp;#8217;ve experimented in the past with things like &lt;a href=&quot;http://nanoc.stoneship.org/&quot;&gt;nanoc&lt;/a&gt;, but Octopress makes it dead simple to set up, generate, and deploy a static &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; blog. If you&amp;#8217;re considering starting a blog, and feel comfortable working in the Terminal, I can&amp;#8217;t recommend Octopress enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of advantages to the &amp;#8220;baked&amp;#8221; approach. Since there are no slow and expensive database calls, it&amp;#8217;s blazing fast, lighter and more responsive, and it won&amp;#8217;t fall down the first traffic spike it gets &amp;#8211; not that I&amp;#8217;m expecting to get &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net&quot;&gt;fireballed&lt;/a&gt; or anything, but for me it also means that it&amp;#8217;s lightweight enough that I can probably get away with running it with a single Heroku dyno for the foreseeable future &amp;#8211; which makes it free. There&amp;#8217;s also a security argument to be made, since there&amp;#8217;s no admin interface to hack, or any chance of &lt;abbr&gt;SQL&lt;/abbr&gt; injection. Finally, I also like that it makes backups really simple: the posts live on my computer, so they get backed up to Time Machine and SuperDuper as part of my regular backup process; my Sites folder is symlinked in my Dropbox folder, so there&amp;#8217;s a backup there too; and since the posts are also under source control, everything gets committed to my Github repo as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few other things of note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The theme is mostly built from scratch, based on the design of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gesteves.com&quot;&gt;my website&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, I mostly destroyed all the sensible patterns and defaults &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/imathis&quot;&gt;Brandon&lt;/a&gt; (the creator of Octopress) created for theming it, so I think I&amp;#8217;ll have to do some work rebuilding them to keep the code more organized. I did keep his awesome port of &lt;a href=&quot;http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized&quot;&gt;Solarized&lt;/a&gt; syntax highlighting, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I modified it for deployment to Heroku. This included, on Brandon&amp;#8217;s instructions, removing the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; folder from &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;, but I also added everything &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; folder and the config files to &lt;code&gt;.slugignore&lt;/code&gt;, to keep the slug size as small as possible (it clocks in at 460 KB, vs. 4.4 MB for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gesteves.com&quot;&gt;my website&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s slug); and I added a rake task for Heroku deployment, which is mostly a copy of the default Github one, but pushing to Heroku &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iawriter.com/&quot;&gt;iA Writer&lt;/a&gt; as my blogging software, so I modified the &lt;code&gt;new_post&lt;/code&gt; rake task so that it calls &lt;code&gt;open #{filename}&lt;/code&gt; at the end, which opens the newly created post in the default editor for Markdown files, which I had previously set to Writer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also symlinked the &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; folder to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iawriter.com/&quot;&gt;Writer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.secondgearsoftware.com/elements/&quot;&gt;Elements&lt;/a&gt; folders in my Dropbox, so I can theoretically write posts from my iPad and iPhone, although I&amp;#8217;d have to &lt;abbr&gt;SSH&lt;/abbr&gt; into my computer to actually publish them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m trying to simplify the process of creating new posts and deploying to Heroku, and integrate it better to the OS. I&amp;#8217;m currently trying to figure out how to add the rake tasks to OS X&amp;#8217;s Services menu. I also replaced some of the &lt;code&gt;puts&lt;/code&gt; calls in the Rakefile with calls to &lt;code&gt;growlnotify&lt;/code&gt;, to get nice Growl notifications on successful deploys and whatnot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I still haven&amp;#8217;t decided whether or not I want comments here, or if I want to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com/&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/reference/plugins/comments/&quot;&gt;Facebook Comments&lt;/a&gt;. In the meantime, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=%40gesteves%20&quot;&gt;tweet @gesteves&lt;/a&gt; with any comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t import any of the old content from Tumblr; I couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out a good way to do it without breaking a ton of links, since Tumblr&amp;#8217;s permalink format doesn&amp;#8217;t match Octopress&amp;#8217;s. I thought about modifing Octopress&amp;#8217;s permalinks and work something out using my local backup of Tumblr, but instead I opted for a clean break and a fresh start, using a bit of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sinatrarb.com/&quot;&gt;Sinatra&lt;/a&gt; code to 301-redirect any traffic looking for a Tumblr permalink to my Tumblr&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://tumblr.gesteves.com&quot;&gt;new domain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;#8217;m not entirely sure how much or how often I&amp;#8217;ll write here &amp;#8211; Twitter &amp;amp; Tumblr seem to have atrophied my ability to write more than 140 characters at a time, and writing this post took longer than I care to admit &amp;#8211; but I do hope to at least comment on interesting web design &amp;amp; development resources I find, in the style of &lt;a href=&quot;http://labnotes.org/&quot;&gt;Assaf Arkin&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Rounded Corners&amp;#8221; series &amp;#8211; which I love &amp;#8211; and maybe get back in the habit of writing well enough to, you know, express, like, opinions and stuff. Wish me luck, and thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
